Hello, welcome.
It is June 18th, 2025
and but your cover slide had me guessing
for sure and we're in active or extreme
9.1 with Manuel Hoffman and with Bradley
Alysia as guest. We will be discussing
their recent paper the value of
open-source software and looking forward
to this a lot to say that I'm sure will
come after your presentation. So thank
you again for joining and to you for the
presentation.
Great. Yeah. Uh fantastic. Thank you
Daniel for inviting me to present this
work and yeah Bradley looking forward to
the discussion and everybody else on
YouTube as well. If you have any
comments, obviously that's uh much
appreciated. All right. Well, so let me
just dive right into this, right? Um so
we're covering here um the value of
open-source software. Um as uh let me
just give you an idea, right? And
probably um you are closer to that than
maybe some of the other audience member
to whom I usually present. But um you
can think about a bunch of companies
here, Google, Ford, Intel, John Deere
and we usually can just ask you know
what do they have in common? Well
actually what they have in common is
that among others they are really
examples of um users and contributors to
open source software and um we know that
open source software is a um really a
cornerstone of modern software
development. So 96% of firm code bases
contain some uh form of open source
software. That's according um to the
software analytics uh company synopsis.
And 76% of all code infirm code bases is
actually um open source software code.
It's um hugely important in cutting edge
technologies, artificial intelligence,
quantu quantum computing, big data and
analytics and uh many other areas. So um
one um venture capitalist Mark Anderson
once said software is eating the world
and that was enhanced by Joseph Js who
um used that saying software open source
is actually eating software faster than
software is eating the world. Um just
talking about the dominance of open
source software um which uh just uh to
give you the rough idea of the
definition right open source software is
software whose um source code is
publicly available usually under some
permissive uh license in particular um
we are interested in free open source
software very often um which is a public
good um it's generally non-rival so if I
consume it there's not less available um
for you and it's usually non-excludable.
So um basically it's the ideal form of a
public good um that everybody can
consume and um often you can really
think of that as a as a global public
good like education um individuals and
firm have used firms have used open
source software and contribute to it
substantially right so there has been a
bunch of literature especially uh by by
my co-author here uh Frank Nigel um but
also a lot of other people and we are
continuously working on better
understanding um the open source
software ecosystem, companies and
individuals that engage in it. Um so now
you're probably very familiar with this
uh slide, maybe I've seen it too often,
this kind of figure, right? um where we
can see this huge machinery of our
modern digital infrastructure and then
there is this little piece at the bottom
which is a project by some random person
in Nebraska that has been thanklessly
maintained since 2003.
So uh what that tells you right there is
um first there is some huge dependency
on some highly active individuals some
open- source maintainers um without um
our without um there could be a
potential collapse of our modern digital
infrastructure and on top of that
there's the issue of the tragedy of the
uh commons which is um that which is
common to the greatest number gets the
least amount of care according to
aristotally right So there's some kind
of free riding uh potential not only but
also I think um issues that we observe
anecdotally and which we also see here
in the data um as well. So now um why do
we care about the value of open source
software? Well, I guess we care about
the value of a lot of goods. Um but here
in particular we do not know um actually
what's the value of open source software
because it doesn't even come up in
traditional uh gross domestic product
measures right that are in accounting
systems and um also some firms may just
not be aware of productivity and
cost-saving benefits. So that's why we
um you know are bringing out this paper
to uh better understand the value of
open source software measuring um the
value here in a very simple way um as
the price um times quantity P * Q and so
here opensource software you have really
the problem the price of open source
software is zero right um there is no
price that is um the actual measurement
problem and the quantity well it's
infinitely replicable um because the
license allows for free copying and
usage is not easily trackable. So we
have a problem on the price side, we
have a problem on the quantity side and
we're not saying that we're going to
solve this problem, but we're um saying
we're going to we're trying to make some
inroads here. So um this in the spirit
of what Warren Buffett said, price is
what you pay and value is what you get.
So right we price could be one idea of
value but it's really not the actual
value and um of course we want to
provide a value measure here because um
usually um a lot of forks managerial
folks firms working in companies but but
really anybody wants to understand um it
wants to get an idea of how valuable
something is. So um because otherwise um
people may not um allocate resources
towards it or do not really understand
the importance of it.
So we ask how much would we lose really
if open-source software did not exist or
ask differently how much would it cost
us to replicate the universe of
open-source code. Um, and for prices,
we're going to calculate uh the prices
using what we like to call a replacement
value or so-called um you could also use
a purchase price. And for quantity, we
will use two large data sets. The
largest ones that we are aware of um one
is the census of open source software
which is um inward facing towards the
within the company the products that
they are using and then um reselling and
then built with which is an outward
facing data set um that is um basically
based it's based on websites and the
usage of of open source software and
website.
Now to measure the value of open source
software you could um or really the
value of any um anything that is
difficult to measure you could go about
it in two ways. You could go about it
from the output market side. Uh the
output market would be the the goods
market from the firm's perspective and
you can just um let's say you have a
good that has a a price of zero. Then
you find a substitute good um that
actually has a positive price and uh you
may be able to impute that to get an
understanding of um what the value may
be. and North House have famously made
this very generary case for greenhouse
gas emissions and um Greenstein Nagel
have for example calculated the value of
Apache um servers being around $2
billion and that has been extended um
with web servers in general the value
being around $4.5 billion and
they could do that because they have had
some information on what the substitute
good was and so so that is very helpful
right um so they have information on
usage of all of the web servers but then
we can only really look at one
particular type of um software here web
servers and it's difficult to expand
that because you would need to find a
basket of goods a gigantic basket for
each of the open source software
packages and some are not um you know
are really small pieces some are larger
pieces it's difficult to find those um
substitut goods. Um so what we did is um
we're going to use the second approach,
the input market approach um or the
labor approach. So from a film's
perspective, you're going on the labor
market and we're going to look at the
replacement value via labor cost. You
can think about that in the spirit of um
household innovations, bicycle and
hipple. Um main idea here really is um
let's think about the housework that you
are doing, right? you're you're cleaning
um something, you're vacuum vacuuming in
your house and you're not getting paid
for that, right? You just do that in
your free time. That's not going to add
to GDP. But you could instead hire
somebody and they could um do the work
and vacuum for you and that would be the
price that it would cost um to do to
engage in this household um activity and
then you could measure the value and um
we are going to do a similar exercise
and we're not the first one here there's
uh blind and co-authors that have done a
kind of similar exercise um for the
European Union um Robins uh and cos have
done an exercise for the United States
where they estimated the supply side
value being around1 billion to 38
billion. We do this um not on the
European or US level but we think about
that as as a global estimate but we are
going to cut down and we're going to
look at firm specific contributions. So
we're going to discard kind of the long
tales of contributions that may um
happen um from from individual small
contributions. So that's where our
estimates may differ. So now the good
thing about this approach is we have all
of open source um we can use all of open
source software and we can assign some
kind of price by imputing the wage that
it would um cost to create this um
product. And the negative aspect is
maybe it's difficult to stay to to get
the usage information. But now um we're
going to um we are also approximating um
the usage information through our two
large data set. So now um for our
methodology we're using really multiple
counterfactuals. Um well we are mainly
using method two but uh in one
counterfactual we're also um going to
use um a part of method one a little bit
and I'm going to explain this in more
detail here. So our first counterfactual
is uh the supply side counterfactual. So
it's the idea that open-source software
as a concept just purely doesn't exist
and now the whole code has to be
rewritten once. Now um we're doing that
by um looking at all open source
packages that are used by companies uh
in particular. Um we uh think about
addressing production externalities. So
um like we are just holding constant
people that are working one company are
not going to move to another company and
are produ or like are not benefiting
from the production of one piece of code
when they are then uh producing another
piece of code. um but they are just
producing those pieces of code
separately. Then um we count the lines
of codes per package and calculate the
labor replacement um value um so which
is for us um in this case the value of
uh from the supply side and we can um
dive into a little bit um how this labor
replacement cost value works exactly um
after going through those three uh
counterfactuals.
Now the second counterfactual is um well
if uh the concept of open source doesn't
exist anymore. Now what would happen is
maybe one firm would rewrite would would
emerge and rewrite the code and then
sell it to all of the other firms. So um
that's
now we would just think about obtaining
the information usage information that
we have from both data set on the
packages we address uh consumption
externalities holding so there are no
additional kind of spillovers then we
sell um the the one seller um gen
creates all of those packages and then
they sell it at the market price P. So
here you can really see that it's just
um the price times quantity over all of
the packages minus the fixed cost that
it um takes to generate um those
packages which is really the value from
the supply side um from the first
counterfactual and the elasticity of
demand here is around one. We did some
um that we set around one um based on
the literature but we um estimated it
and varied um it so engaged in some
robustness checks that you can find in
the papers as well paper as well. And so
the main idea is that we find an optimal
price P here given all of the quantities
and then we can um create uh then we can
get a measure of the overall value from
a one seller demand side. Now a third
counterfactual is what we like to call
the firm auto key demand side and um
this concept of open source software
again doesn't exist anymore. Now each
firm has to write rewrite the code by
themselves. Um we again obtain all of
the usage information address
consumption externalities but now
there's a single replacement idea within
a firm. So when you use um when you use
a product yes you can use it multiple
time a package but we are really
thinking of that um we don't have to
generate that there's no additional
value that is being generated from using
it additional times because you're just
using you can just um freely move it
within the company and um there's no
price for internally using it. Now we
calculate the value here by using the
supply side value and multiplying it by
all the times that it has been used each
package um for each of those companies.
All right. So um what is the data about?
Well, we have the uh Census 2 of free
and open source software which has been
um a really a mega project I would say
by my uh co-author Frank Nagel at um
HPS. Um and this is uh from uh 2020 data
from 2020 in particular. There is a
third version um coming up and there are
continuously new version and we're
trying to see how we can get more
information about open source software
usage that is particularly firm related
and here you can see uh code usage of
firms globally. So there are around
600,000 packages but we are going to
really uh home into the top packages. So
we're cutting off a huge tail um on on
the right side. Um this is information
from software composition analysis
firms. So they are scans. What those
companies um here Synopsis and Sneak for
example or FOSA are doing is they're
usually asked um to
scan um
all of the usage of um
open source software and software in
general within firms. For example, when
a merger is happening um of firms or
before a merger is happening because the
companies want to know what kind of
potential liability exists and um so
they really check for license
compliance.
Now um a second data. So this is the
kind of the inward facing um data set um
that um we construct and the second
complimentary data set is from built
with which um is a um service which
basically scans all of the websites um
globally and gets the code from all of
them and then um it measures all of the
technologies that are embedded in those
websites and among others. this cont
contains um all open source software web
development and we try to approximate
that we think here an underestimate we
are just basically fing focusing on
JavaScript um to make it easy on us but
I'm sure um there would be uh you know
like there's an even larger value here
those are 8.8 8 million websites. We
wanted to home into the ones that are
distinct from websites. So we match this
with a a couple of uh company
databases that allows us to identify
companies. So like compost and pitchbook
which gives us around 3.3 million
websites for um almost the entire year
of 2020.
Now we have those two complimentary data
sets. There are internal faith
internally inward and outward facing and
um additionally for um for an analysis
on on inequality and what the
contributor what the developers
contribute as a value we uh use GitHub.
we um obtain the share of contributions
to a project um from developers. Um so
really the commits to a project and the
number of project contributions
and um as the fourth data set that has
been um relatively recently added are
firm contributions. So we try to obtain
an understanding of firm affiliations of
projects through the emails of the
committers. So if you used an email that
is um
tied to a company that we can identify
in August compost or pitchbook where um
or is this a global database on
companies and compost is um for for
public firms and pitchbook for for small
for smaller entrepreneurial firms. um
then we would attribute that to be a
firm affiliated project and um we get
the share of commits that are uh firm
affiliated per project.
Now um I mentioned we are using this
kind of replacement value labor cost
approach. So we are really using the
constructive cost model also called
Cooko from the USD department of defense
to estimate software project cost. It's
quite a flexible model but we just we
are going ahead with the default
parameters but again we're engaging in
some robustness checked with those
parameters as well. So really here it's
here the effort stands for person months
effort. So how many people do you need
per month and then LOC stands for the
lines of codes and thousands of lines of
codes. And we just have uh some
parameters here that we um that are
nonlinear transformation that we uh that
we can vary but we use a default um for
this exercise. And um
one aspect is well once we know you know
how many people we need um then we also
need to provide give an idea about what
the wage for those individuals may be
right and so from salary expert another
database we got uh the monthly gross
salary uh with the range from 3,000
to$10,000
um dollars um so from a low and high
wage country. Let's see if this button
works properly. Um so here you can see
the top 30 country countries that are
included um for what we call the the
global wage. Um so we included 80% 88%
of GitHub activity from 2020 and we used
all of those company in the global in a
global wage estimate. So we really have
three estimates. One is um you like um
an estimate where we used um a low wage
from India, one where we used a high
wage from the US and something in
between with all of those countries that
I just show you as a as a global average
wage.
All right. Now,
to give you a sense of the data, here
are some uh descriptive statistics um
for both panel A, which is uh the
sensors and built with data in um panel
B. So outward and or inward and outward
facing. So you can see the lines of
codes for all packages. In particular
here the number of pack like yeah the
lines of codes is roughly um maybe 70%
of that um when we just focus on the top
five languages and we can see um the
usage of all packages around two 2.7
million times that packages were used
here. the um around 1,800 or packages or
for the top five languages around 1,600
packages. Build has a little bit has
also roughly the same ratio of top five
languages that we identified based on um
GitHub's uh top five languages um during
that time period. And I show you what
those um where um when I go through the
results um but those are around 740
projects.
All right. So now um the comes here's
basically the main finding right if you
want to take um anything away from this
it's um it's here the value of open
source based on pure code so we're
getting rid of any kind of addition what
could be uh data for example or could be
m maybe machine generated and um what we
find is for a low wage country would be
the Indian wage we found around $1
billion value on supply side of firm
related open-source software um packages
where there's a global estimated around
4 billion and six billion on the higher
side for US wage um as a value. Now, um
when you have one seller that is taking
and that is recreating everything and
then selling the packages to those
different um firms that are using it, we
have almost we have basically a constant
value of 5 around five trillion dollars.
Um there is some variation but basically
the wages here don't matter as much
because they're in the fixed cost. Um
and then finally when we assume that all
of those companies have to replace um
open source software packages by
themselves internally and they don't uh
resell sell products to other firms.
Then we get a value of around um $88
trillion um globally um in this case.
Right? So you can see this look at this
as some kind of upper bound and maybe we
may be in between this one seller case
and the firm auto key case in reality.
Now um well let's take a the 5.25 25
trillion as kind of a lower bound
estimate, right? Um you accounting in
particular for usage. So not just the uh
supply side of your availability of
packages. And so this is around right
5.25 trillion in demand side value over
the time. Um in particular measured in
the year 2020. And we know that private
firms spent around 45% of um software uh
cost on prepackaged software um so
proprietary software right so now uh
let's assume this kind of spending that
is actually US estimate holds globally
um this would be around $2.36 trillion
um of proprietary um spending on on
closed software if you like now you add
the value of the 5.25 25 trillion to
that it's around $7.61 trillion
just purely in software cost. So what
that implies is that firms sp firms now
would spend 3.2 times more on software
than what they currently are spending um
in relation to uh because open source
software the concept just purely doesn't
exist anymore in this um world, right?
Um so that's a huge um kind of
costsaving for them um when you just
think about open source um software
being freely available.
Now we know there's a substantial value.
So one question that is quite natural
here is how evenly is this actually
distributed? Well, and here are some
examples of um well, this is here the
top five languages plus um Go um from uh
from GitHub. And you can see um this is
a supply side value of just recreating
um all of open source software once um
of the top five languages. There's some
substantial variation where Go and Java
um you know have quite a high value. Um,
Python for example has a relatively low
value. Type code JavaScript also
relatively low value on the supply side.
Um, see somewhere in the middle. Now um
this is not surprising. This is more of
a robustness uh check um on the supply
side for so this was a census data set.
the inward facing, the outward facing
build with data set. We conditioned
already on JavaScript which is often
also related to TypeScript and so we
picked up B basically all of that
variation um in in the externally facing
data set. Now for the sensors of open
source software unfortunately we don't
have any information on the hetrogenity
by industry. So we try to um think about
that a little bit more in the context of
um the outward facing build data set and
we got some we could show you some
hetrogenity in the demand side value of
the trillions of dollars. So we can see
um here in administrative and support
and waste is quite high the value
healthcare and social assistance
professional scientific services other
services quite high retail trade also
relatively high or you see um
manufacturing interestingly it's
somewhere somewhere in the in the middle
I would say um management of companies
and enterprising mining and public
administration utilities or agriculture
is um the value is relatively uh limited
it and to some degree that may be just
of uh lower uh yeah just substantially
lower usage in those industries.
Now um how is this value distributed or
or I guess where does this value come
from? Um when we think about the
developers here and we plotted a
Lawrence uh curve. So with this idea of
a genie coefficient of being one right
um if you have this if you think about
the Lawrence curve here as tracing the
45 degree line this is the um share of
the value on the supply side. This is um
the um y-axis on the x-axis you have the
cumulative share of developers that are
creating this value and they're creating
um they engaged in uh repositories. Um
here the value is in blue and the
engagement repositories in uh orange.
Now if this blue line would be exactly
aligning with the 45°ree line that would
mean that every developer contributes
evenly contributes equally really to uh
the value share but we don't see that.
We see that the um that this blue line
here that is the value line for the
share of developers is actually very
close to the corner here and very far
away from the 45 degree line and that's
what we would expect also from the
literature right um that there is a
share of developers that is um here
maybe around um five or 10% of
individuals that are creating a
substantial value. They are generating
most of the value here on the suppliers
that are creating the packages. And
interesting so um interesting part here
is that they are not just active in a
few projects but they're active here in
yellow in in many many different
projects on average.
Now um we could go to the one seller
demand site. We actually see a very
similar picture here. um the we see a
huge inequality of just a few um
developers contributing a substantial
amount to the value share and we see
this again um when we look at the firm
auto key case so now um to conclude here
from um the inequality story 5% of open
source software developers will
liquidate 93% of the supply side value
and as a bound 99% of the firm auto
demand side value. Um so just the 5% of
developers create a huge amount of value
um on the supply and the demand side.
Now what about the firm uh the value
that firms uh that is kind of firm
affiliated right that potentially firms
are creating. Well um what we find is
that 23% of projects are firm
affiliated. Well um that implies that
77% are not. Um now firm contributions
to the value of open source software uh
look as follows. We see the share is
around 6% of the firm contribution to on
the supply side on the one seller and
firm auto key it's between 7 and 2.8%.
So the firm contributions here are as
measured by the thermal radiation which
may be an underestimate here right but
it's um actually quite low. The
interesting aspect is that they supply
more than they demand based on those um
usage statistics. Um also very
interesting if you think about um you
know individuals here certainly create a
lot of value in this space but uh firms
are also doing valuable things when you
just uh think about correlations of uh
film affiliated uh repositories. Um here
in uh like reddish and then in kind of
like this blue color you see non-firm
affiliated um
the the shape the density distribution
um for the t days from the last commit
measure which implies um here that firms
are really um substantially more active.
the distribution is very close to
relatively more close to zero than for
individuals and that
may imply that firms projects are just
more actively maintained and that is
overall a good thing. Now um there are a
bunch of reasons why we may think that
um what we're finding here is the value
of open source software uh that we
actually underestimating the value. Um
the global data that we have is very
particular global data uh from those
software composition analysis firms
which is as good as um what we could get
as data but but the you know global data
is still incomplete. We cut off the tail
of the distribution as mentioned. We
also got rid of comments, documentation,
empty lines, anything that is not pure
code. Um, we have an additional estimate
for that in the paper. Um, also you can
think about code being improved over
multiple versions, right? We are not
accounting for that and that is but that
is also costly. And you could also
imagine well there are a bunch of um
projects that a company has to um work
on and not all of the projects may work
out but so it may be a necessary process
of to have a lot of project failure with
one successful project but that implies
that there are also costs that are
associated with those kind of failures
and those costs are not um included
here. Now um we also think that even the
highest wage scenario is kind of a lower
bound on wages because if you think
about the individuals that some of the
individuals that are active in this
space they can obtain um especially
highly skilled individuals in open
source they can um obtain quite high
wages u from some of the um big tech
companies. Now further we just don't
have the Linux kernel in here which is
probably um yeah a huge uh value driver
u when it comes to open source software.
Now to conclude the value of open source
software on the supply side is around $4
billion with a one seller demand side
value of 5 trillion which can go up to
$80 trillion when firms are um just
recreating codes by themselves. We find
hetrogenity across industries and
developers where 5% of develop
opensource software developers create
around at least 93% of the value and um
firms here make up really a small share
but projects are a bit more actively
maintained um by or projects by firms
are more actively maintained than by
individuals. So without open source
software there would be really a large
loss in value. Firms would need to spend
3.2 two times more on software than they
currently do. Oh, thank you so much.
Thank you.
Awesome. Lot there.
Big iceberg. Only small amount showing,
right? Perhaps first uh Bradley maybe
introduce and and coming from the
open-source sides that you've worked on
like where does this take you? what does
this reflect on you? Yeah, so um you
know I I come from a bit of a different
perspective. I I do a lot of open-source
uh education and and project management
and then I've worked in open source not
in in terms of how corporations
interface with it so much but how
basically you can do scientific research
with open source and other types of
things like you know creating games with
open source and I liked what you had
here. I think that was a very good
analysis of looking at like sort of
putting a value on
you know what we have out there and um
but I I I wonder especially with respect
to like the active inference aspect you
know is it that people are motivated by
money or is it that there in some cases
they're motivated by sort of a need in
the in the communities they're working
in and in the sort of the you know cuz a
lot of like if we think about Linux and
some of the things that have been
created there it was largely because
there was some utility of a tool that
they needed and there wasn't a tool
anywhere else. So they created the tool
and then they made it into this thing
that was distributed and then it went
from there. So the original motivation
was actually more kind of like almost
like maybe reinforcement learning or
something like that. And then you know
when you get into when once it's
distributed then you have this uh
financial imperative that might take
over or this sort of um cost imperative
like cuz I know you showed that figure
of the maintainers and how they play
this critical role in open-source
projects and and you know a lot of the
problem there stems from people not have
you know kind of doing it on the side
and then not having enough time to
devote to actually maintaining these
large packs. packages. So, you have
these vulnerabilities cuz people just
don't have, you know, it may start that
they love the project and they're
motivated by self-interest, but then
over time you get, you know, a project
that's so big that maintainers just
simply can't afford to do that, you
know, to spend like 70 hours a week
maintaining this project. So, I mean,
you know, I wonder about that. Like,
what are your thoughts about different
types of motivations for open-source um
production?
Yeah. No, I think you're absolutely
right. um like the motivations um
especially at you know like the origins
of open source and I think even what is
created right now as open source
software tools is very often yes there
we need some kind of tool we don't have
it and so let's create it and um I guess
that's the origin of a lot of
innovations just generally speaking um
like or that's one of the idea of
innovations right like um I I don't have
this particular thing I a need and now
well if nobody else is doing this I'm
going to do it but they're willing to
also share this you know like the open
source community um to share uh things
openly that's the whole spirit of it so
yeah I think um non-punary benefit like
non-picurinary motives are a huge driver
of what is going on how open source
software exists in the first place right
and um this idea of sharing and
supporting a
potential even like reputation building.
And there are some you know aspects of
course where this then like like it's
also kind kind of like a skill building
exercise but maybe people don't do that
necessarily just for that purpose but it
comes with it. Then the like once you
create those kind of projects and are
really successful in it as you point out
then maybe you don't have the time
anymore to even uh be able to maintain
those uh projects. uh just for free. Um
but then you have learned a substantial
amount on the way which uh is quite is
valued quite highly in the marketplace.
So companies I think do value that and
we have seen papers around that where
where people even try to signal um hey
like I'm I'm contributing to you know
like open source by engaging in a couple
of commits before I'm getting hired and
then after that you can see kind of like
a drop off in um the engagement. Um but
um I think yeah there are many different
motives but certainly the nonpunary
motives is um quite a critical one in
this environment. I completely agree.
Yeah. So I mean the other Oh, go ahead.
Go ahead. Oh yeah. So the other thing I
wanted to mention is that like you know
the way kind of we do open source is
kind of dependent on certain tools that
we have. So you know we have forks of
repositories
and you know that makes it easy for
people to say copy a repository and make
modify it and distribute it and it's
really interesting. I wonder if you know
people thought about like the economic
sort of benefits of a lot of the
innovations of uh version control where
you have like forking
and you have like you know being able to
control different versions and how
they're distributed because that that
kind of plays a key in like how people
get value out of it. If I see a project
I want to fork it. I want to create like
I want to basically add value to it,
change it so that it's useful to my
field or my group and then you know if a
thousand people do that that's a lot of
value out there and if you can't do that
easily then there the value is limited
because it makes it harder to sort of
keep all the distributions maintained
and keep all them all consistent.
So, you know, there are all these tools
that kind of showed, you know, were kind
of before we had the kind of version
control we have now. It was probably
much harder to get value out of the open
source software. It was just kind of
like people kind of distributing it
maybe on discs or, you know, there were
earlier versions of version control. And
it would be very interesting to see
where that sort of started up if that if
there were like the set of innovations
that we have say with GitHub
played a huge role in kind of like
kickstarting a lot of the value of open
source.
Um yeah that's a great point and we are
um in constant communication with the
guys at GitHub and have some other work
with uh the people at GitHub and and
generally yeah I agree with that also um
like the benefits of version control I
would think are enormous I mean they
just contribute to this I like to
outsourcing in general right um but but
I I haven't seen a paper on that so
because I I guess it's difficult Yes, we
can look into the past uh and there will
be we're getting value out of it. Okay.
Sorry. Um I think you're a little bit
frozen.
Okay. Um now you're back. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Um yeah. So just right. So you
mentioned this point of disks um you
know like code being distributed on a
disk versus now with the later version
controls the ones where everybody can
access it. And I think this would be uh
yeah it would be very useful to
understand the world where we just have
disks versus the world where we just
have where we have the version control
that we have now but have those two
worlds right next to each other. And
it's it's as difficult as our exercise
that we um did in this paper because we
have to imagine different kind of
counterfactual worlds and then try to
impose some assumptions. I'm sure this
can be done or maybe there's a clever
way of of of getting an understanding of
what you know the benefit of version
control is. I'm sure that just the pure
number of people that are getting pulled
in right you can you're just building on
on you know pulling in the crowd
substantially more and making it more
convenient for everybody to contribute
in a very easy way and that's why open
source software is I think also
successful because um of yeah
crowdsourcing and um yeah you're just
very easily
there's a there's zero cost basically
from you replic vicating a package.
Yeah, just to this last point, we're
still very generationally early in the
global internet facilitated exchange of
open-source software. So it's kind of
like looking at the early developmental
phases and and there's a lot of core
technologies like Git and services like
GitHub
and there may be other facilitating
technologies to open source overall.
Um some that people are probably working
on like ways for payment channels or or
credit assignment to propagate back um
upstream uh different ways to think
about the um the value and security of
it. Like the part about the paper and
the presentation that that um was most
interesting to me was these different
economically grounded estimates which
differed by orders of magnitude
ultimately. So it was a very restricted
and humble analysis
because and then because it didn't
include Linux, it included some packages
on some services from some companies.
And so it's kind of like turning on the
flashlight to use economically
normal normative estimation methods,
different ways of triangulating what
just the economic narrow value like
software with a price tag would be let
alone this training
improvement of infrastructural type
software. So just just that even when so
restricted
still there was a wide range of
estimation.
So I guess how how does estimation move
forward
and then what do those estimates who do
you tell about those estimates
or who who who do you who do you want to
see do what if they were to know that a
given method of value assessment were
this or that? Mhm. No, this a great
point. I think part of um I think there
are some efforts in um yeah in
government and um when it comes you know
to estimating GDP in general and we
would love to see um
an a version um brought into the GDP
right where you can estimate the where
the value actually impacts um GDP
measures that would be fantastic of
course this doesn't mean that um what we
have used here needs to um be
incorporated. One has to really um think
about what's you know like an optimal
version for that. But also just
generally speaking I think um provide I
think providing those different
estimates is helpful for um first
providing one estimate I think is
helpful when you talk to anybody that
has not even an idea has not even heard
about open-source software right there.
Some people may just go on the internet,
they use some code and they're happy
that they found it and they are, you
know, very new to the space and you can
um you can pull people in with hey, you
know, this is a giant space um and it's
an extremely valuable space. So that's
one even when you look at the lower
bound estimate I think um I like to
think about that as I had some work on
vaccination prior to the pandemic and I
had to explain um you know to people the
importance of that and I feel this is
kind of very similar for open source
software when you talk to um people that
are not in the space they are not going
to appreciate it as much and even some
of the people that are they just um you
know like use it there's a lot of free
writing going on which is okay but um
there's also some aspect of you know
like there's a lot of value created and
how can this be sustained and yeah so I
think informing everybody first about
the value is important it's also
important um not just for society as a
whole but also when you think about
companies in particular managers um
there are some organizations that have
actual like open-source software units
maybe uh and developers are using open
source software tools but then um when
they're engaging in their work um they
have to also justify to their managers
why are they doing what they're doing
right and what kind of value they are
creating and if they can't do that it's
kind of uh challenging to talk to their
manager the manager will be like I don't
know what you did um but I know exactly
when we buy a product from Microsoft
that cost me x dollars and um yeah so
and I don't know that you know like
what's what's the cost when we do this
here with an open source software tool
and finding the right comparison and I
think that's where we should be going um
so that um yeah open source so that
people can justify the usage of it
within companies even more I think that
would be great if if this paper can just
make a little bit of a dent here um in
the general perception and perceptions
at the workplace around open source
software as well. Yeah.
Yeah. I think that quote that you had
there the price is what you pay value is
what you get and it's the value of open
source software and then there's like
this deeper psychology to paying or
valuing what has been provided
and the different sensitivity to losing
what already is there as opposed to
gaining what could be and all these
different types of costs like time cost
tech burden those things come up in the
industry setting and in the research
setting. So again, it's just sort of
like opening up some paths to explore.
Well, if every firm had to redevelop
just some JavaScript packages, we'd be
talking about like the economic activity
of the whole world. So we know we can't
do that. So okay, so we're going to talk
then we're going to have some sharing of
code. So then what does that look like
in in some sort of extreme world where
every firm develops every package and
every operating system and like even the
largest uh corporations can't develop a
secure Linux kernel to there's one
version of everything. Somehow everyone
knows how to find it. There's one
package for every single thing. Um
where are we? Where do we want to be?
Where is the redundancy contributing to
resiliency
and to to maintaining portfolios of
different approaches even if there's
like multiple visualization packages for
a given language? It's sort of like it's
not necessarily wasteful,
but just to be able to assess that and
then to say, well, here's here's if we
were to move this way,
this is these are the kinds of costs
that would and wouldn't show up on the
accounting sheet of a firm.
These are the costs that society would
or wouldn't incur
over these different time scales. Like
here's how much this software would cost
to buy today. But then over the longer
time scale, maybe there's less
opportunities for participation in skill
development or research
and that has a a vast cost as well.
So how does that get addressed in that
sort of techno tragedy of the commons?
Yeah, I mean also I mean obviously we're
not addressing this in the paper. Those
are very deep questions and um I think
it's yeah it's very challenging to to
think about um like you know let's say
you have a bunch of packages that are
all doing something that is very similar
as you point out. Is this necessarily
wasteful? Maybe not because we can think
about like this just as an evolutionary
process, right? um like we need a couple
of um projects or ideas out there and
then some of them over time will survive
and they will be selected by um you know
whatever you want to call the best in
this case maybe the one that just is in
highest demand. Um but there or like
there's some kind of lock in effect
because people have used it for some
things um initially and then um you know
that's why we're why this particular
package will be used uh all the time. Um
so yeah so I think there's an
evolutionary aspect uh to that question.
Um but I I also agree on like
sustainability of the environment and we
need to find a way of especially once
you know their packages have risen to
prominence substantially whatever that
means right there there may be some kind
of threshold of uh demand. Then we have
to think about um can can the community
support this? Are there or can there be
company efforts? Can there be new models
um on supporting the the open-source
software environment? Um because those
packages that are used substantially,
they are contributing substantially to
the value um of open source software,
not just on the individual side, but
also uh from a company perspective, even
though they're maybe not as engaged. And
so that's one of the really the bigger
picture questions that I see is also
like how to pull in uh companies that
are currently benefiting so much and um
yeah like so that they are paying part
of the cost but also getting something
in return even maybe even more than what
they're getting right now by um
contributing to this ecosystem in a in a
in a way in a way where it stimulates
simul innovation that is potentially
beneficial for for them, right? And you
can't ask a firm to maximize profits and
um you know do engage in things for free
but um there can be a profit motive in
the long term and engagement and
innovation and I think that's generally
true for innovation. So yeah, so find
figuring out those models um I think are
is hugely important and you mentioned
yeah I think initially you mentioned
like services like that that we in the
initial phases of um or early phases
still um
of open source software development
right we in like I don't know by which
measure if it's like uh 30 years or 50
years or whatever the a good measure is
for That's that's hard to hard to say
but um yeah so there are services like
git and github and the version control
kind of ideas out there but yeah and
there may be new services like uh for
example codeql where AI is uh
substantially used to then u provide you
with ideas of well here is maybe a
security problem right and you can fix
that and then you can use AI or you can
you don't have to um to fix it um and so
Those are additional tools that um
became available and are becoming
available and maybe some of them are
more difficult for beginners than than
others. Um but I could also see that
some of them could rise to prominence.
uh similarly but they of course we talk
about those AI tools again this can come
with pit pitfalls um as well when we
have the whole environment flooded
potentially by AI generated code um and
we all know that that can um then the AI
has potentially less training data that
is not not unique anymore um but yeah
that's that may be a different story but
there are moving into the space of AI I
guess there is um there are more and
more kind of tools where a few of them
may survive. You think about this
evolutionary aspect again.
There's this concept. Yeah. Yeah.
Please. So there's this concept and I
don't know if you're familiar with it. A
lot of tech people like it. It's called
technical debt where when you adopt
something maybe you're locked into some
solution and you and it costs you as an
organization. So, I mean, you know, I
wonder how the value of open source fits
into that where you're losing value
because you're locked into a suboptimal
platform, but you're also there's an
opportunity to gain value by maybe
adopting working around it through open
source or being able to modify your
software.
Yeah. Yeah, I think that's right. Um,
right. So this technical debt issue with
with a lock in problem that pro probably
exist um is higher this kind of
technical debt when you think about
closed um form like closed software
proprietary uh software that you're
locked in and you maybe even have a
harder time because you need um
maintainers that are you know you have
only a limited set of individuals that
are familiar with this particular
software while in for open source
software you potentially have always new
people that could come in and look at
the software and um yeah you can adopt
it more easily. Um so you can switch
more easily. Um fixes can be generated
more quickly. Um just the whole idea of
crowd sourcing. Um so I think there yeah
generally technical debt as you would be
as you are saying is um is going going
to be lower with open source uh
software. um you need to have the I
guess like the right like still services
around open-source software for
developers to then actually engage in
all of that uh type of work right um and
I think there are companies out there
are people out there that are doing
exactly that you just have to you know
work with the right people um but like I
guess in terms of how that impacts the
value of open source software um
it's a good question I would I think it
leads to a potential underestimate here
again, right? Because it's just um so
much more like e like you just have less
of a of of a burden here. And um so so
the value is automatically higher
because you can you can switch more
quickly from one innovation to another.
But what exactly that value is that is
uh hard for me to say or like how to
measure that. Um but yeah, intuitively
that would be um again contributing to
the idea of underestimation. Yeah, it's
a great point. Yeah, it reminds me of
the the economic estimates like every
window could be broken and then we would
be adding value by just rebuilding. So
that's the kind of rebuild approach
which and then that that risk or like
strategic value of like using an open
schema or offsourcing or having the
opportunity for people to offsource uh
and then how to quantify like the value
of optionality or of resilience to
certain kinds of technical changes or
like if you're relying on a proprietary
software even for like a microscope in a
lab or simulation toolkit and then the
company slows down or goes out of
business or or you know any number of
other things. Whereas like if you have
the source code it'll never get worse
than it is. Maybe one of its
dependencies could have like a future
security issue but you'll always have
that local function. And that's sort of
what we need for the scientific
reproducibility either way where like in
the neuroiming
uh community it there's a well-developed
stack to talk about which versions of
which software are used that that
Bradley and colleagues have shared um
previously and also Pedro writes in the
live chat there is implicit trust given
to companies that build in the open. So
that's value for the companies or for
the labs who are able to put out this
useful
thing.
Uh Bradley if you have any other
comments otherwise Manuel
I will look forward to hearing like okay
yeah what are your what are your next
moves what are exciting directions and
and how you're continuing this research
or other projects?
Um yeah sure. Well yeah thank you. Um
yeah this is great. Um I really like
this discussion. Um in terms of the
value of open source software what I
would like to see which is very
difficult. I would love to just see a
map or have a map of usage um and maybe
not just usage but really then the value
created um across the world. I think
that would be a you know ambitious
endeavor that's very tough especially
because you have to you know some of
this information is proprietary and
exactly in this instance here we were
not able to get such granular
information where we could where we were
able to map everything to every region
in the world but I think that would be a
great descriptive starting point for an
an addition for this value of open
source software project and just
generally um figuring out more
information on usage across the world uh
within companies um what are the which
kind of packages are used when and where
I think it's extremely valuable and
important and yeah so I think that's on
the value of open source side now I
started a little bit talking about AI um
get around that but so now the value of
open source software one thing that we
are pondering uh about is um what about
the value of open source um or
opensource AI if you like and we can you
know think about what that concept
actually is but um there's of course
this a similar discussion that was that
is around software generally right open
world is proprietary which uh I think is
not has been basically
or is basically concluded almost where
open source software one and um now a
similar discussion exists in the space
of AI, right? Should it be open versus
closed? And uh so we would like to
understand like what's the value of
open-source AI relative to closed form
alternatives? Um that would be you know
in the spirit of this project. We would
love to better understand that as well.
But I think there's also a lot of work
even before thinking about AI. Um yeah
on on how to um yeah better understand
the value maybe across industries even
more. um we did this just for the
externally facing data set. If we can
really dig into an internally facing
data set and are able to um show some of
the estimates across industry, I think
that would be fantastic. But again also
that hinges on finding the right uh
organizations, companies that are
willing to share some of those that
information that we need uh to then um
engage in our value estimation. And
another one is um you know sharing ju
just the methodology broadly speaking
and hopefully the methodology being
adopted more widely even um you know
let's say on GitHub or any kind of open
source uh platform where people could
get a rough sense of an like value
estimate right and and this won't be
perfect by any means but it's it's
something that uh at least is a little
bit more tangible uh so that would be
great uh great tool
Um yeah so I think that's what we're
doing in terms of um better
understanding the value of open source
software we have also um other projects
in the space of open source software um
in particular we have a project that is
more on generative AI and better
understanding um GitHub copilot and how
it affects the nature of work of
individuals so that's that's I I think
an exciting project which is not as you
know closely tied to this project here
but where we just try to see how work
patterns are changing when you have
access to um this generative AI um
coding tool and we see that people seem
to engage in more coding that's u kind
of project management activity and we
see a lot of like kind of
experimentation
um out there a little bit less of
exploration and can uh at the end of the
day um yeah we see that people are
engaging more autonomous and less
collaborative work um because they you
know like they can use the AI tool
instead of um engaging with the
community where um which we like to call
a project management is really engaging
with uh other developers on the issues
board and then assigning other
individuals and um yeah at the end of
the day um in terms of experimentation
new we find that people are engaging
more um exposing themselves more to new
languages that are worth more in the
marketplace and we were able to use that
to to put a color value kind of also
very much like back of the envelope
calculation to um the GitHub copilot uh
coding AI which is a couple of uh
billion uh dollars uh just for exposing
yourself to new languages. So yeah, we
always try to think about, you know, the
value that is generated um for the
community or when the community
interacts um with tools with open source
or with with tools that are intersecting
with the open source uh software space.
So yeah, I think that's super exciting
and and happy to chat with anybody or
also emails are more than welcome and
any questions. Thank you. Thank you. I
think maybe in the future we will hear
more from your research and a scientific
open-source metaanalysis
Bradley andor other in uh the audience
that could be very interesting to trace
back some of those and and just talk
about it from a scientific computing
value chain rather than the industrial.
Yeah, sure. Sounds good. Yeah, that's
great to hear. Cool. Thank you.
Appreciate it. See you next time. You
too. Thank you so much. Thank you.